I'm going to answer any questions you have about home loan insurance refunds in
this video.
Information from A to JD related to home loan insurance
refunds. In this video, we'll
answer questions like:
what will happen to the insurance if you
transfer your home loan? What will happen to home loan insurance in case of a death claim?
How will you receive a claim? You've taken a home loan top-up, and
you've been provided with insurance under that as well.
What will happen to the previous one?
I've made 50 payments and repaid the home loan.
Despite that, the
insurance EMIs are still the same. What will
happen if you don't have the second home loan insurance papers? The
loan has been closed. How much
refund will you get? I'm going to answer other important
questions like this in this video. So,
watch this video until the end.
If you want to know what will happen to the insurance of the old home loan after the home loan is transferred, then the
clear answer is that
when you shift your home loan to
another bank,
you must have closed the loan from the previous bank and have
its NOC.  You will have to get that NOC from the
insurance company, that is, the
person from which you had taken the home loan earlier, from which bank or NBFC, you have to
get the NOC from that company and you have to mail it to the insurance
provider who was the insurance provider of the past company
or
talk to their customer care and
provide them the NOC within 15 days by
giving some basic documents. You will get
your refund money within 15 days, if there is any remaining amount,
you will get it
within 15 days. What will happen to the insurance if the person taking the home loan
dies,
friends, I will
explain it to you in detail that
if you took a home loan and
you took an insurance along with the home loan,
your insurance is active and is
absolutely operational and in that situation the
person taking the home loan dies, if
he is insured, then
what will happen in that situation, in that
situation,
when the insurance company which has given the insurance feels that
all the things are valid and okay, then in that
situation they  Whatever claim benefit
you have been told as a lump sum,
its benefit is
given to the home loan company and that home loan
company reduces your loan by adjusting it in your loan, that is,
whatever loan
insurance benefit
you get is reduced. That is why
whenever you take a home loan and the insurance you take along with the home loan, every minute detail of it is
written in your sanction letter or your insurance bundle. Once you
verify with the customer care
what insurance benefit you will get,
whether you will get any benefit in case of any disease
or in case of accidental death,
this minute information is with your
insurance bundle or the
insurance company
because different loans have
different details. So what you have to do in that situation is
how will you get whatever benefit is there. I am telling you once again
that home loan  The loan giving
company must have done an insurance, the
insurance bond will be with you, you have to
talk to the customer care of that company and tell them
that the insured person has died in this way,
you have to provide the death certificate,
after giving the death certificate,
if the insurance giving company simply
validates everything, then
whatever will be your death claim benefit, it will be given
to the home loan giving company by the insurance
provider and that money will be adjusted in your home loan, if
you still have some questions related to this, then you can comment below, if insurance is also added under the
home loan top off, then
what will happen to the previous loan,
friends, let us understand this with an example,
if you took a home loan,
took a certain amount under the home loan, then the bank
insured it, that amount has
already been insured by the bank, it was
secured for your earlier home loan,
but you take a top off, that is,
you take the fund again, then every
single thing is added in it again, that is, the bank
He also wants to secure that re-given loan which we call top off,
which we also call home loan top off
insurance. So friends, the earlier
insurance will remain for the earlier loan
and the insurance given with the top off taken has been
insured to secure that amount. You have paid 50% of the loan.
Now what will happen to the insurance?
Friends, if you have taken any home loan of
50 lakhs, you have
paid 50% of it, that is, you have paid 25 lakhs.
Now the burden of your home loan is
only ₹ lakhs, but
this insurance was only on your loan of 50 lakhs.
I am taking this as an example,
if you had insurance of 50 lakhs
and your
balance is only ₹ lakhs, then in that situation the
capping of insurance
remains the same, there is no change in it, that is,
whatever is insured for your loan,
it is completely covered.  If your insurance is above Rs 50 lakh, then if
you want to make any changes in it, then
for that you will have to contact the insurance provider
and tell them
that
if there is any remaining amount in your insurance amount, then it should be
refunded to you because your loan
surcharge is only Rs 1 lakh. So, for
all this information, you will have to
contact the insurance company.
What to do if you do not have home loan insurance papers?
Which company has given you the home loan, if
it has insured you, then which
company is providing you the insurance,
who is the insurance provider,
you will have to contact them,
talk to their customer care and
give all the information about yourself that
my insurance is provided by your company,
these are my basic details,
this is my mobile number, name, email ID,
you will have to provide all these basic details
and they will provide you an insurance
bond either physically or online from
which
you will get all the information about
which type of insurance you have been given.
How much amount has been taken, how much amount is not,
you will get the total information
but first of all you will have to get all your details validated by
talking to the customer care of the insurance company, the
home loan has been closed, how much refund will you get,
friends this is the information, many people have
asked this question, I will give you a simple
answer to this, you took a home loan and
you got it insured and at the same time
you closed the home loan before time, then
how much money of the insurance will you get,
I will explain it to you technically in detail,
whenever you take a home loan, the
insurance that is given with it,
a certain premium of the insurance is taken from you, let us
assume that the premium is
of ₹1000000, as an example, let me
assume that the premium is of ₹1000000
and it has been given to you for 5 years, then
if seen from the principle,
what is the rule of ₹2000000, so how much amount is
left, how much is left or not, it depends on what
you have done  How long ago the loan was closed
or after how much time the loan was closed,
all this information will be provided to you by the insurance
company that how much
actual refund you will get after closing the home loan.
Still, if you
want to ask something related to this, then you
can comment to me. What documents are required for home loan insurance refund?
Friends, if you have taken a home loan and
you have taken any insurance along with the home loan,
if that home loan has been shifted to
some other bank, hence you
need a refund or you have closed the loan itself,
hence if you have any remaining home loan insurance
refund money, then you
need that, then what documents will have to be provided for that?
You will simply have to provide PAN
card, Aadhar card, along with Aadhar
card, you will have to
provide a cancelled cheque, the cancelled cheque will have to be provided in the
account in which you want the refund money. I am
telling you the basic things, you will have to provide
PAN card, Aadhar card and cancelled cheque,
along with a photo, you will have to
write an application that you want the refund money.
Most
I am telling you about the important document that will be required. NOC.
What will the NOC be required for? If you have
closed your home loan, whether it was
done in the form of balance transfer or you have
closed the loan with your own funds,
you must have received an NOC for that.
You have to submit this document. You have to provide this document to the insurance
company which has been your insurance company in the past. It takes
15 days. They
transfer the money into your account in which
you have provided a cancelled cheque. Is it
necessary to take insurance with a home loan,
friends, you will know the answer to this now.
Suppose you took a home loan and the
company provided you an insurance along with the home loan.
This means
that you are being insured for a certain amount and a certain
time.
If the person
dies during that time, then whatever is the claim
benefit will be adjusted in your loan
and the surcharge on your loan will be
reduced. Friends, I want to tell you one thing that this is
not compulsory at all, as per my experience.  According to him, it is
not compulsory to take home loan insurance
but because it is a benefit for you,
life is uncertain, so in this
situation you should keep your loan
secure and you should
definitely get your home loan insured.